A Guide to the Papers of J. Carson Adkerson, 1913-1981
Special Collections Department, University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Papers of J. Carson Adkerson, 1913-1981
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
10244-a
ca. 6,500 items (15 Hollinger boxes, 5 linear shelf feet)
The papers of J. Carson Adkerson, 1913-1981, consist of chiefly correspondence, financial and legal papers, press releases, reports, photographs, bound volumes, and miscellaneous papers, pertaining to Adkerson's career in manganese production and as president of the American Manganese Producers' Association.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
The papers of J. Carson Adkerson were given to the Library by Miss Clara Lee Miller of Woodstock, Virginia, on February 7, 1986.
Biographical/Historical Information
J. Carson Adkerson (1892-1985 ?), of Woodstock, Virginia, was a mining engineer in manganese production. He served as president of the American Manganese Producers' Association (1927-1962). The importance of manganese lies in its use in the production of steel where it is utilized to remove undesirable oxygen, to neutralize the harmful effects of sulphur, and to impart physical characteristics to steel such as hardness, toughness, and resistance to abrasion.
Scope and Content Information
The papers of J. Carson Adkerson (1892-1985 ?) consist of ca. 6,500 items, 1913-1981, chiefly correspondence, financial and legal papers, press releases, reports, photographs, bound volumes, and miscellaneous papers, pertaining to Adkerson's career in manganese production and as president of the American Manganese Producers' Association.
The correspondence series contains correspondence between Adkerson and many of the American manganese mining companies about legislation affecting the industry, problems with mining the ore, efforts to convince Congress to pass the Strategic Materials Act (approved June 7, 1939) in anticipation of possible wartime conditions, accompanied by copies of letters to various congressmen, efforts to convince Congress to pass legislation to boost the domestic production of manganese, manganese producers conflicts with the United States Steel Industry who preferred to purchase their manganese ore from cheaper foreign producers, and discussions of promising manganese properties to be developed.
Other files in this series discuss manganese problems and possibilities by state, representing most domestic manganese producing regions, and related topics, such as the "Buy American" bill, the Railplane System, and the Manganese War Claims bill.
Specific topics or correspondents, mentioned with their folder heading, include: the Strategic Materials Bill, "To provide for common defence by aquiring stocks of strategic and critical raw materials" (1939), and Wilbur D. Mills (April 1, 1942), both in the Otter River Mining Company file; and Harry F. Byrd (April 29, 1938), in the Properties file.
The American Manganese Producers' Association correspondence includes: the steel industry's side of the dispute over use of domestic manganese ore (April 28, 1933), Carter Glass (February 13 & 18, 1933), Fagbagan Company (May 14, 1934), A. Willis Robertson (August 14, 1936 and March 15, 1939), Strategic Materials Bill (June 3, 1939 and July 2, 1940), Harry F. Byrd (March 26, 1940), E.R. Stettinius, Jr. concerning manganese production (July 11, 1940), and a comparison of Russian and American manganese industries (September 28, 1940).
Others include: the effects of the National Recovery Act on employment in manganese ore mining (August 5, 1933), and arguments concerning the domestic manganese ore and the desirability of foreign ore for the production of steel (June 5 & 17, July 3 & 14, and September 12, 18, & 25), in the file on Alabama, Arizona, and Arkansas; American Federation of Labor President, William Green (June 26, 1936), in the Delaware and Washington, D.C. file; and George H. Dern (May 5 & 26, 1934), and Daniel C. Roper (May 7, 1934), in the Railplane System file.
Companies or individuals represented in the second series of business and legal papers include: J. Carson Adkerson, the American Manganese Producers' Association, Biggam Manganese Company, Clough Manganese Corporation, Fagabagon Company, E.J. Lavino & Company, W.F. Maginnis, Otter River Mining Company, Raw Materials National Council, Reconstruction Finance Corporation, and Unicoi Manganese Company. Adkerson was personally involved in the operation of many of the companies included in this series.
The printed material series includes: copies of legislative bills, maps of various manganese properties, Mineral Industry Surveys, newsclippings and press releases concerning mineral and manganese production, and miscellaneous printed documents.
The fourth series is concerned with articles and reports about manganese production and properties.
Series five consists of miscellaneous papers, including the personal papers of Adkerson, an official program of Franklin D. Roosevelt's Third Inaugural, a petition of the American Manganese Producers' Association to Roosevelt, photographs about manganese mining and one about the railplane system, the minute book of the AMPA, a photograph album of the Cuban American Manganese Corporation Isabelita Plant, Studies for the Application of the Railplane System of Transportation in Rio De Janeiro, the Biggam Manganese Company Ledger, a scrapbook regarding manganese production, a pay ledger for the [Tennessee Manganese Corporation], and oversize photographs about manganese mining and oversize certificates awarded to Adkerson.
Organization
This collection was not received in any distinguishable order. It was arranged in five series:
1) Correspondence (boxes 1-4)
2) Business & Legal Papers (boxes 5-7)
3) Printed Material (boxes 8-10)
4) Articles and Reports
A. Miscellaneous Articles & Reports (boxes 10-11)
B. Reports re Manganese Properties (boxes 12-13)
5) Miscellaneous Papers (boxes 13-15; 2M Ledgers; OS Tray 53; OS Box P-1 ).
Contents List
- Correspondence (Box 1-4)
  - Alabama, Arizona, Arkansas 1933-1936 (Box 1)
  - American Manganese Producers' Association 1929-1959, 3 folders (Box 1)
  - "Buy American" Bill 1946, 1955 (Box 1)
  - Clough Manganese Corporation 1942-1944, 1946, 1950-1951 (Box 1)
  - Colorado 1933-1937 (Box 1)
  - Costa Rica Properties 1950-1951 (Box 1)
  - Delaware, Washington D.C. 1933-1937 (Box 1)
  - Domestic Manganese Production 1933-1957 (Box 1)
  - Embree Iron Company 1943 (Box 1)
  - Fagbagan Company 1918 (Box 1)
  - Florida, Georgia 1933-1936 (Box 1)
  - Georgia Properties [John A. Foy] 1946, 1950-1951 (Box 1)
  - Glade Mountain Corporation 1941-1945, 1949-1951, n.d., 2 folders (Box 2)
  - Goodwin, C.I. - Manganese Mining in Va. 1942-1943 (Box 2)
  - Industrial College of the Armed Forces 1950-1951 (Box 2)
  - Interstate Manganese Corporation 1945 (Box 2)
  - Luna Manganese Company 1941-1947, 1949 (Box 2)
  - Manganese - General 1940-1943 (Box 2)
  - Manganese War Claims 1944-1946, 1952-1954 (Box 2)
  - Manganese War Claims Bill 1947-1949, 1955-1958, 2 folders (Box 2)
  - Manganese War Claims Bill - Congressional Letters 1947-1948, n.d. (Box 2)
  - Manganese War claims Made by Shinn 1944-1946 (Box 2)
  - Michigan, Minnesota, Montana 1932-1935, 1937, 1941 (Box 3)
  - Mills, Wilbur D. 1962 (Box 3)
  - Miscellaneous 1928-1964 (Box 3)
  - Nevada 1930, 1932-1934 (Box 3)
  - New York, North Carolina 1932-1937 (Box 3)
  - North Cove Mine, North Carolina 1942-1944, n.d. (Box 3)
  - Oregon 1937 (Box 3)
  - Otter River Mining Company 1938-1942, 5 folders (Box 3)
  - Pennsylvania 1932, 1934-1937 (Box 4)
  - Personal 1929, 1933-1952, 1962 (Box 4)
  - Properties 1919, 1929-1959, 2 folders (Box 4)
  - Railplane System 1933-1934, 1938 (Box 4)
  - Strategic Materials Corporation 1960-1961 (Box 4)
  - Virginia Polytechnic Institute to Biggam Manganese Company 1942-1943 (Box 4)
  - War Production Board to Unicoi Manganese Company 1943 Feb 16 (Box 4)
  - Wartime Production of Manganese 1940-1945, 2 folders (Box 4)
  - Washington, West Virginia, Wisconsin 1933-1936 (Box 4)
- Business & Legal Papers (Box 5-7)
  - Adkerson, J. Carson: Business & Legal Papers 1916-1949, 1954-1956, 1981 (Box 5)
  - American Manganese Producers' Association 1929-1937, 1946, 1951, n.d. (Box 5)
  - AMPA: Duplicate Receipts 1946 (Box 5)
  - AMPA: Financial Statements 1947-1951, 5 folders (Box 5)
  - AMPA: Financial Statements 1951-1954, 3 folders (Box 6)
  - AMPA: Traveler's Expense Books 1952 Aug-1954 July (Box 6)
  - Biggam Manganese Co.: Business Records 1942-1946, 2 folders (Box 6)
  - Biggam Manganese Co.: Legal Record 1941-1946 (Box 6)
  - Clough Manganese Corporation: Business & Legal Papers 1944, 1947, 1950-1951 (Box 7)
  - Fagbagon Co. 1930 (Box 7)
  - Glade Mountain Corporation: Business & Legal Paper 1943-1944, 1949-1950 (Box 7)
  - Lavino, E.J. & Company 1943 (Box 7)
  - Maginnis, W.F.: Legal Papers 1939-1943, 1949 (Box 7)
  - Otter River Mining Company: Ditcher Records and Mining Data 1940 Jun (Box 7)
  - Railplane System: Legal Papers 1933-1934 (Box 7)
  - Raw Materials National Council: Articles of Incorporation 1936 (Box 7)
  - Reconstruction Finance Corporation: Legal Papers 1945-1950 (Box 7)
  - Unicoi Manganese Company: Business Papers 1942-1943 (Box 7)
  - Unicoi Manganese Company: Legal Papers 1941-1943 (Box 7)
- Printed Material (Box 8-10)
  - Legislative Bills 1933-1961 (Box 8)
  - Maps: Batesville, Arkansas Property 1952 (Box 8)
  - Maps: Lincoln Investment Corporation Properties 1917, 1925, 1931 (Box 8)
  - Maps: Miscellaneous 1942, 1950-1959 (Box 8)
  - Maps: Powell's Fort Mine Property, Shenandoah County, Virginia 1918, 1950, 1957 (Box 8)
  - Maps: Santiago, Cuba Manganese Property 1919 (Box 8)
  - Mineral Industry Surveys 1948-1977 (Box 8)
  - Minerals & Metals Commodity Data Summaries 1961 (Box 8)
  - Newsclippings 1927-1976 (Box 9)
  - Press Releases 1919, 1930-1962, n.d., 4 folders (Box 9)
  - Press Releases: Barter Program 1958-1963 (Box 9)
  - Printed: Miscellaneous 1927-1980, n.d., 3 folders (Box 10)
- Articles & Reports (Box 10-13)
  - Miscellaneous Articles & Reports
    - Bureau of Mines Exploration Projects 1945 (Box 10)
    - Federal Aids for War Mineral Production 1942-1943, 1950, 1954 (Box 10)
    - Federal Loan Agency and National Defense 1941 (Box 10)
    - Ferro-Manganese, Spiegeleisen, and Manganese Ore 1928 (Box 10)
    - Heavy Media Separation with WKE Portable HMS Plant 1954 (Box 10)
    - The Madaras Steel Process 1951 (Box 10)
    - Manganese and National Defense 1943-1962, 2 folders (Box 10)
    - "Manganese General Information" 1933-1940 (Box 11)
    - Manganese Plant for the Cuyuna Range 1942 (Box 11)
    - Manganese Special Grades & Specifications 1959 (Box 11)
    - Mineral Dressing Laboratory re Beach Sand 1949 (Box 11)
    - "Morris Process for Making Direct Manganese" 1953 (Box 11)
    - National Stockpile and United States Strategy 1955-1956 (Box 11)
    - "Phosphate Rock" 1958 (Box 11)
    - Portable Manganese Processing Plant 1954 (Box 11)
    - President's Cabinet Committee Report on Minerals Policy 1954 (Box 11)
    - Problems of Small Business and National Defense 1943 (Box 11)
    - Railplane System 1929-1933, n.d. (Box 11)
    - Smelting of Manganese Oxide, Carbonate, or Silicate Ores 1942 (Box 11)
    - Strategic Importance of Manganese and Steel Supply 1942-1960 (Box 11)
    - The Strategic UDY Process 1958-1960 (Box 11)
    - War Minerals Claim Bill (H.R. 834) - Truman's Veto 1950 (Box 11)
  - Reports re Manganese Properties
    - Alabama 1947 (Box 12)
    - Arkansas 1929 (Box 12)
    - Bering Straits [ca. 1937] (Box 12)
    - Costa Rica 1950 (Box 12)
    - Georgia 1918 (Box 12)
    - Marau, Bahia 1956 (Box 12)
    - Miscellaneous Property Reports 1914, [1929], 1940-1941, n.d. (Box 12)
    - New Mexico 1950 (Box 12)
    - North Carolina 1930, 1941-1943 (Box 12)
    - Otter River Mining Company Properties 1940-1942, n.d. (Box 12)
    - Pennsylvania 1945 (Box 12)
    - Tennessee 1915, 1916, 1940 (Box 13)
    - Virginia 1913-1957, n.d., 2 folders (Box 13)
    - West Virginia 1932-1936 (Box 13)
- Miscellaneous Papers (Box 13-15; 2M Ledgers; OS Tray 53; OS Box P1)
  - Adkerson, J. Carson: Astrological Data 1930-1933, 1952, 1954 (Box 13)
  - Adkerson, J. Carson: Biographical & Personal 1915-1981 (Box 13)
  - Biggam Manganese Company Ledger 1941-1943 (Box 15)
  - Certificate of Mining Engineer belonging to J. Carson Adkerson 1921 Oct 25, oversize folder (small) (Box P-1)
  - Certificate for the Economic Mobilization Correspondence Study Course, Industrial College of the Armed Forces, Joseph C. adkerson 1951 Nov 15, oversize folder (small) (Box P-1)
  - Certificate for Registered Professional Engineer, District of Columbia, J. Carson Adkerson 1952 Sep, oversize folder (small) (Box P-1)
  - Items Pulled from Volumes 1929-1982, n.d. (Box 15)
  - Minutes Book of the American Manganese Producers' Association 1927-1930 (Box 14)
  - Miscellaneous Papers 1929, 1942-1948 (Box 13)
  - Official Program of F.D. Roosevelt's Third Inaugural 1941 Jan 20 (Box 13)
  - Petition of the American Manganese Producers' Association to Franklin D. Roosevelt 1934 June 28 (Box 14)
  - Photo Album, "Cuban American Manganese Corp. (Cuban Mining Co.) Isabelita Plant" [Brett B. Hurff] 1937 (Box 14)
  - Photographs of the First Annual Convention American Manganese Producers' Association 1928 Sep 10-11, oversize folder (large); 3 photographs (Oversize 53)
  - Photograph of "Isabelita Mill," Cuba ca. 1937, Panoramic Photograph
  - Photographs: Miscellaneous n.d. (Box 14)
  - Photographs: Manganese Mining n.d. (Box 14)
  - Photographs of the Second Annual Convention American Manganese Producers' Association 1929 Sep 9-10, oversize folder (large) (Oversize 53)
  - Scrapbook re Manganese Production 1921-1929, oversize volume (Oversize 2M)
  - Studies for the Application of the Railplane System of Transportation in Rio De Janeiro 1937 (Box 15)
  - [Tennessee Manganese Corporation, Erwin, Tennessee?] Pay Ledger 1942-1943, oversize volume (Oversize 2M)
  - Unidentified photograph of a manganese mill n.d., oversize folder (small) (Box P-1)
  - Unidentified photograph of two men on bulldozers n.d., oversize folder (small) (Box P-1)
  - Unidentified photograph of a mill n.d., oversize folder (small) (Box P-1)